The war against the Cerulean Death is over.
「蒼淵呪病」の戦いは終わった
バントーラ図書館は数多くの犠牲と引き換えに
In exchange for considerable sacrifices,
Bantorra Library narrowly emerged the victor.
かろうじて勝利を得た
Two months after it ended, the book of
a Church clergyman was unearthed.
二ヶ月後　神溺教団員の「本」が一冊発掘され
By reading it,
その内容から　彼らが信じていた天国が
本影音版权属其出版、发行方，字幕制作仅供学术交流之用 请于下载后24小时内删除，并不得有公开传播或作商业盈利之行为 若有违法等相关行为，诸神字幕组恕不承担任何法律或连带责任。
a hypothesis was born, stating that Heaven,
in which the Church believed,
夢を操る事のできる
was the dream of a certain sorcerer,
whose ability was dream manipulation.
ある魔術師が生み出した夢であったという仮説が生まれる
翻译 koki  放 晴  La Fatalité
We continued searching, but found
no other devotees' books.
以降も捜査は続行されるが
ほかの信徒の「本」は発掘されず
压制 暗之亚瑟王  校对 凉YAN Lucifer 时间 Lucifer
この仮説が　結論として神溺教団の正体とともに世界に公表された
This hypothesis was announced to
the world, as the final word
on the truth about the Church.
Today's book is about a man so lucky,
he'll make you green with envy.
今日の「本」はなんとも羨ましい幸せが記されていますよ
He had five wives, each with a
different eye color and skin tone.
目の色も肌の色も違う　五人の妻を手にした男
お気に召さない
Not interested?
You've had no appetite of late.
ここのところずっと食欲がないようですが
しかたない
Oh, well. You can wait then, can't you?
待っていただけますかね
Until the new Governor of Paradise creates
a book that'll knock your socks off.
新たな楽園管理者が
飛び切りの「本」を作り上げる
その時まで
诸
神字幕组
剥がれ落ちた夢 澱む幻
The dream that's fallen away
and the stagnant illusion
もう この世界を見放した者さえ
The words embrace even the ones
who have abandoned this world
包み込む言葉
刹那に消えゆく
Disappearing instantly
共に囚われの明日を取り戻そう
Let's take back the imprisoned
tomorrow together
何もかも失くしても
Even if we lose everything
最期の審議の日まで　ずっと
Until the judgment day
Keep on blooming proudly like flowers
花のように強く咲き誇れ
絶望のオト　拾い集めて
Pick up the sounds of despair
永久に奏でる　ストレインに変える
Play it forever and change it into strain
I'll stick around, clinging onto the subtle light
僅かなヒカリ　すがりついても
留まるから
届けたい　残らず
I want to convey it until there's nothing left
第23话 脱狱
与
Episode 23
A Jailbreak, a Tool, and a Desert Violet
道具
和
沙漠之紫罗兰
Sir... Sir...
顧問　顧問　起きてください　顧問
Please wake up, sir.
Please wake up, Governor of Paradise.
お目覚めください　楽園管理者様
Don't call me by that name!
貴様　名前で呼ぶな
Master Minth, advisor to the Margund
Foundation for Humanity's Advancement,
マリグント人類進歩財団の顧問　ミンス様
these are the materials on the new
candidates to become True Men.
こちらが新たな「真人」候補の資料になります
Another one of those women...
お主も食えん女じゃろう
これが…
This...
意外だろう
Didn't expect it, huh?
俺も最初に見たときはそう思った
The first time I saw it, I felt the same way.
I'm used to being disillusioned...
幻滅にはなれとるわ
Because I use the Sacred Eyes.
聖浄眼でな
I knew that the Acting Director and you guys
were guarding a pretty major secret,
代行やお前らがでかい秘密を抱えとることも分かっとた
じゃがな　まさかこのタイミングで言われるとは思わなかったが
but I didn't expect you to approach me now.
カチュアの愚行で壊滅した神溺教団を立て直し
We will rebuild the Church that
that idiot, Kachua, destroyed
もう一度世界に平和をもたらす
and restore peace to the world.
And you're the only one who
can lead that effort.
それができるのはお前しかいない
ミンス＝チェザイン
Minth Chezine, you are hereby appointed
the next Governor of Paradise.
お前を次代の楽園管理者に任命する
Do you accept, Minth?
受けるか？　ミンス
なめるなよ　マット
Do you think I'm an idiot, Matt?!
分かっとるわ　受けるしかないってことぐらいよ
I know I have no choice but to accept it!
I accept! Because I'm the
only one who can do it!
受けるわ　わしがやるしかないんだからだ
ミンス様は　神溺教団から争いを排除なさいました
You were the one to put an end to the
Church's war plans, Master Minth.
Rather than surrounding yourself
with greedy Mock Men,
良心を持つ「擬人」だけを部下におき
you are gathering conscientious True Men
with pure hearts and virtuous wishes...
欲望を叶えるためでなく
善な願いと純粋な心を持つ「真人」を集める
It's commendable.
ご立派です
Save your compliments.
お世辞はいらんわ
なかなか愉快な面子が揃っとるな
You found some real characters for me, huh?
A banker who keeps trying
to climb icy mountains.
冬山に挑み続ける銀行員
ロケット通機械を作って宇宙へ行こうとしとる科学者
A scientist who's trying to build something
called a "rocket" to go into space.
An old man who works at the Morall market?
モールアルの市場で働く爺さん
That's not far from here.
ここからそう遠くないな
Ah, yes...
あー　彼はほかの「真人」候補と違いデータがそろってないのですが
Unlike the other True Men candidates,
I have no gathered data on him.
However, he possesses a wish
that is incalculably grander
常人には計り知れない　強い望みがあるようです
than that of a common man.
切れたな
Out of tissues.
You put on a reluctant face,
いやいやのわりには　ずいぶん仕事熱心ですね
but you're surprisingly serious about your job.
I have some shopping to do, anyway...
買い物がてらじゃ
うん？
わい　大丈夫かよ
Hey, is he all right?
汚ねぇな
That's gross. Poke him to see if he's alive.
お前触って生きてるか…
Pardon us.
そこ　すまんの
彼です　顧問
Sir, it's him!
We were too late.
遅かったか
Apparently, he was transporting
sand and dirt until his death.
死の間際まで　土砂運びをしていたようです
No one knew who he was.
誰も彼の筋を知らないと
こんな老体がそこまでして
Working so hard in such a decrepit body...
What was your wish?
お主の望みはなんだったじゃ
I'm impressed you homed in on him.
彼に目をおつけになるとは　さすがです
Lascall.
ラスコール
Congratulations on your promotion
to Governor of Paradise.
楽園管理者ご就任　おめでとうございます
Like it's something to celebrate!
めでたいことなんじゃあるかい
さっさと済ませ
Do what you have to do and leave.
その「本」は「真人」だっち噂があってな
Word is that that's a True Man's book.
May I have it?
渡してもらおうか
H-Hey!
おい
Relax.
ご安心ください
この「本」をお届けするのは
I will be delivering this book to
someone you know very well.
貴方様もよくご存じの方でございます
What did you say?
なんじゃと
What a lovely night.
いい夜ね
You know, I couldn't even die
in the Cerulean Death war...
「蒼淵呪病」の戦いでも死にそびれちゃったわね
Maybe I should wish on a shooting star.
流れ星にでもお願いしようかしら
I've started to think you're not
serious about wanting to die.
本当に死ぬ気があるとは思えなくなってきたが
Hey, Hamy, how do you hope to die?
なあ　ハミ
お前はどんな死に方が望みなんだ
Well...
そうねえ
普通に結婚して
I could get married, like a normal person,
普通に幸せになって
be happy and have my family watch
me go, with tearful eyes...
家族に涙で見おくられて
Man, that'd be about the
lamest way possible to die.
そんなださい死に方は絶対嫌だけど
What's lame about it?
それのどこがださい？
The one day a year when we forget
our duties and party like fools...
年に一度　全ての職務を忘れ
ただのお馬鹿に戻って騒げる武装司書パーティー
The Armed Librarian party!
Yay!
イェー　のわりには　まったく盛り上がってませんね
Except no one's partying...
What do you expect?
仕方ねぇ
We've lost too many
brothers-in-arms this past year.
この一年　失ったものが多すぎる
Also...
それに　これからとんでもないイベントが待ちかまえているからな
We're waiting for a wild event to begin.
Where are Yukizona and Yuri?
ユキゾナとユーリは？
They're still convalescing.
また　静養に入ったとよ
Rich people have it so easy.
暢気だよね　お偉いさんは
They don't understand what
we have to go through.
あたしらの気も知らないでさ
This is Noloty's book. Enlike brought it.
エンリケから送られてきたノロティの「本」だ
What?
え？
What on earth?!
これは…
That can't be...
そんな　ダルトムさんが神溺教団と繋がっていたなんて
Dulltom was connected to the Church?
Yes. "Volken killed Bizaku."
あ　ヴォルケンがビザクさんを殺した
その情報を俺たちに流してきたのはダルトムだ
Dulltom was the one who
fed us that information.
Not one of us actually saw Bizaku's death,
俺たちは誰もビザクさんの殺された瞬間どころか
nor his book.
ビザクさんの「本」すら見ていない
So then, Volken Macmani was innocent?
それじゃ　ヴォルケン＝マクマーニは無実
I don't know.
分からん
But Volken did say he was going to expose
the Acting Director's wrongdoings.
が　ヴォルケンは代行の悪事を暴くと言っていた
口封じのために殺された可能性もある
It's possible he was killed to shut him up.
レナスさんも消え出すからね
Renas vanished, too...
And Minth quit the Armed Librarians
without even saying goodbye.
ミンスさんもなんの挨拶もなしに武装司書を辞めちまったし
In any case, I do know one thing.
とにかくあたしらに分かることは一つだよ
Kyasariro...
キャサリロさん
The Acting Director is hiding something from us.
代行はあたしたちに何かを隠している
And because of that...
そのせいで…
Starting with Noloty, we've lost many comrades.
我々は　ノロティを始め　多くの仲間を失った
Sorry I'm late!
悪い
代行
Acting Director.
What's this? You haven't started yet?
あらら　まだ始めてないの
As this is the one day a year we Armed
Librarians can forget our duties,
今日は　武装司書が武装司書であることを忘れられる年に一度の日
we are going to break one
of Bantorra's rules
我々はバントーラの掟を犯します
that the Acting Director demands
our absolute obedience.
館長代行には絶対服従であるという掟を
Gamo, you...
ガモ　お前
All right. So you're saying the
festivities are about to begin.
そう
楽しいパーティーをこれからおっぱじめようっていうのね
Man, this is boring!
うんー　つまらないの
You could have skipped the trial and
gone straight to the punishment.
裁判何てすっ飛ばして　御仕置きしてくれちゃってかまわないのよ
And why did you willingly come here?
それより　なぜ進んでこんな場所に
I wouldn't have cared if you'd waited
in your quarters instead.
代行室に待機していただいてかまわないのですが
It's a formality.
一応　儀礼としてね
If I'm not locked up, I might run away,
閉じ込めとかないと逃げちゃうかもよ
just like that boy.
あの坊やみたいに
So cold...
冷たい　なんか思い出しちゃうね
This brings back memories.
I'm coming in, Hamy.
入るよ　ハミ
Get out of my sights!
うせろ
Hurry and finish it, Hamy.
早く完成しなよ　ハミ
Struggle all you want. It won't do any good.
どんなに暴れたって　何も変わらないよ
Get out of my sights, tool!
うせろ　どーけ
Stop that, Hamy.
止めなよ　ハミ
You know deep down inside you love me.
本当はチャコリーが好きなくせに
You won't even let me indulge my emotions.
考えに耽ることもできないの
I brought a certain book to you.
ある「本」を　お持ちしました
Wow. It's not often you bring me a book.
あら　あたしに届くなんて珍しいわね
あ　この「本」は…
This book...
Seems I have to go out and
put her out of her misery...
そろそろ殺しに行ってあげなくちゃね
The Violet Sinner.
菫色の咎人
The Acting Director's missing?!
代行が消えた
Yes! I discovered it when I went to
bring her breakfast this morning.
そうなんす
今朝食事を持っていたら
やっばり逃げちゃった　裁判はまだ今度ね
"I escaped, after all."
"Let's hold my trial some other time!"
魔力プロペラ機も消えてる
The magic-powered prop-plane is missing, too!
Start searching!
探せ　代行を探せ
Find the Acting Director!
Hamy...
ハミ
We believe the magic-powered
prop-plane the Acting Director took
代行の乗った魔力プロペラ機は
昨夜未明に出発したと思われます
left sometime last night, before dawn.
導き出される先は　イスモの南西
It was headed toward southwest Ismo.
Enlike, can you hear me?
エンリケさん　聞こえますか
It's Milepoc Finedel.
ミレポック＝ファインデルです
I read Noloty's book.
ノロティの「本」を読みました
我々は代行に対立する意志を固めました
Our resolve to mutiny against the Acting
Director has been strengthened.
しかし代行が消えてしまった
However, she's missing.
And here I thought my plan was derailed...
予定が狂ったと思ったが
Interesting.
そうか
Enlike, losing Noloty hurt us deeply.
エンリケさん　ノロティを失ったことで
我々は深く傷付きました
Noloty gave her life battling the Church,
as they sought Heaven...
彼女が命をかけて戦った神溺教団の求める天国は
But Heaven was just a dream.
ただの夢だった
But that's why I want you
to return, to help us find...
でもだからこそ　代行を探し真実を知るために
the Acting Director and learn the truth.
あなたが戻ってきてほしいです
You're mistaken, Milepoc.
違うぞ　ミレポック
Heaven exists.
天国は　ある
If I were to inscribe a word on the
book's spine, I'd put "Penance."
「本」の背表紙に文字が刻まれるとするならば
「懺悔」
It would likely become my book's title.
それが俺の「本」の題名となるだろう
Indulge me, Heaven. Have a drink with me.
なあ　天国さんよ
一杯ご一緒しましょうや
The upper ranks and the lower
ranks both spilling their guts...
上司と部下が腹割って話し合う
That's what makes for a great organization.
それでこそ　いい組織ができるってもんですぜ
Back then, in my youthful anger,
あの頃の俺は　若さゆえの憤りから
I thought of revolting against Heaven.
天国への反逆を考えていた
あんたの願いのせいで　こちとら死人の大バーゲンですよ
But thanks to your wish,
we had quite the bargain for dead men.
一体何を考えているのですかねえ
What on earth was I thinking?
Can you kill me?
僕を殺せるか？
I've sacrificed countless men in an
attempt to make my dream reality.
僕は自分の夢のために多くの人を犠牲にした
However, I've come to realize
it's an impossible dream.
しかし　その夢は叶うことがないことが分かった
I want you to kill me.
殺してほしい
I am a pathetic shell of myself,
unable to realize my dream,
夢をあきらめることも
夢を実現することもできない
and yet unable to let it go.
この哀れな身を
あなたの夢とは　なんですか？
What, exactly, is your dream?
知る必要はない
You need not know.
ただ　僕の夢を叶える手段は二つある
However, there are two ways for it to come true.
一つ　完全なかけることのない幸福を手に入れること
The first is to obtain absolutely
perfect and flawless happiness.
そしてもう一つある
And the second
この世界を滅ぼすことだ
is to destroy the world.
So, if you don't wish to see
the world destroyed,
この世界を滅ぼしたくないのなら
kill me.
僕を殺せ
天国を　殺す
Kill Heaven...
Interesting.
なるほど
I abdicated my title of Acting Director
and built a research facility...
俺は代行の任を降り　研究施設を作った
All to engineer a tool to destroy Heaven.
天国を滅ぼす道具を作るため
I got Hamy to be quiet.
ハミを黙らしといたよ
Okay.
ああ　ハミにはすまないことをした
I feel bad about what I did to her.
チャコリー　お前にも
And what I did to you too, Chacoly.
そんなのどうだっていいよ
Oh, I don't care about that.
それより　父ちゃん
But please, Dad, won't you tell me about him?
彼の話をして
Chacoly...
チャコリー
早く一緒になりたいよ
I want to be with him,
to love each other,
愛し合いたい
and then to die in each other's arms.
そして一緒に死ぬんだ
You've brought back some
painful memories, Makia.
いやなことを思い出させてくれるじゃない　マキア
He's already turned into a book...
すでに「本」になってしまっているというのに
なぜあの老人の調査を続けるのですか
So why do you continue to
investigate that old man?
We watched as he died and
his book was taken away...
目の前で死なれて　「本」まで奪われとるんじゃ
The thought of ignoring that
makes me want to puke.
落ち着くのも胸糞悪い
Also, the look on that dead old man's face...
それにあの老人の思想だな
You looked with your Sacred Eyes?
聖浄眼ですか
Yes.
あー
相は執拗　思考は虚脱　望みは天国
His dominant trait was persistence.
His thoughts were of burning out.
And he wished for Heaven.
天国？
Heaven?
砂漠に菫が？
Violets in the desert?
顧問
Sir.
うん？
Things are kept pretty tidy in here.
中はきれいに片付いとるな
Hamyuts Meseta?
ハミュッツ＝メセタ
This one, too. And this one.
これも　これも
代行のファンか？
A fan of the Acting Director?
通好みじゃの
Whatever tickles your pickle...
That girl... Sir.
彼女は？
顧問
R-Right!
待っとれ　今はずしてやるからの
Hold on. I'll unshackle you.
Wha
な…　代行？
Acting Director!
I've come to kill you.
殺しに来たわ
あの日　殺さなかったあんたを
Since I didn't do it back then.
That was the day Kachua sent
me to kill the Violet Sinner,
あの日　私はカチュアの依頼で
砦に立てこもった菫の咎人を倒しに赴いた
who was locked inside the fortress.
He turned out to be quite a handful,
ずいぶんと梃子摺らせてくれたわね
the lead man.
鉛の人間さん
Long time, no see.
久しぶりじゃない
That's right. That man could never love you.
そう　あんた　あの男に愛されなかったのね
If I kill you here and now,
and read your book,
今ここであんたを殺してあんたの「本」を読めば
I'll know everything you know.
あんたのしたすべてが分かるわ
However...
だけど…
I could let you, a girl no one could ever love,
誰にでも愛されるはずのあんたが
continue to live in this pathetic world,
一番愛されたい男に拒絶された世界で惨めに生き永らえる
rejected by the man whose
love you most desired.
That could be fun, too.
それも面白いかもね
Where do you think you're off to?
どこ行くつもり
ハミュッツ
Hamyuts.
Chacoly...
チャコリー
こ、これは？
Y-You...
It's your fault, Makia.
あんたのせいよ　マキア
Hamyuts, you...
ハミュッツ　お前は…
There's no way I'm just letting
you leave her to rot and die.
ただ老いて死ぬなんて　絶対に許さない
I want you to dispose of the
tool you, yourself, created.
自分の作った道具の後始末は自分でなさいの
最後までね
Makia?
マキア？　どこかで聞いたことがある名前じゃ
I've heard that name somewhere...
He served as Acting Director three terms ago.
三代前の館長代行よ
How was it, Chacoly?
どうだった　チャコリー
Living in a world in which no one could love
you, for the sole purpose of atonement,
誰からも愛されない世界で贖罪のためだけに
being taken care of by that disgusting old man...
あの胸糞悪いじいさんに世話をやかれて
You'd have been better off dead.
死なんて目じゃない
Each day was like having your body torn apart.
毎日が身を切り裂かれるようだったでしょう
All we've got is Ruruta Coozancoona.
私たちにはルルタ＝クーザンクーナしかない
そう育てられてきたんだから
That's how I was raised.
Ruruta Coozancoona?
ルルタ＝クーザンクーナ
There are no people left to watch over you.
もう面倒をみてくれる人間もいなくなった
If we leave you here, you'll simply
wither away over time.
このまま放っておけばあんたは緩やかに死ぬだけ
I'm not so evil a person that I'd do such a thing.
あたしもそこまで悪党じゃないからね
今　殺してあげる
So instead, I'll kill you now.
な、なに言っとるんじゃ　保護してやらんと
Wh-What are you, nuts?!
We need to protect her!
Love me... Love me...
愛して　愛して
Please love me.
チャコリーを愛して
What the heck?
なんじゃ
離れなさい　ミンス
Get away from her, Minth!
Love me... Please love me!
愛して
チャコリーを愛して
Olivia Litlet said so...
オリビア＝リットレットは言った
The Church of Drowning in God's Grace
was born from the Armed Librarians.
神溺教団は武装司書から生み出された存在
They worked together
やつらは天国に真に幸いなる人の「本」を運ぶため手を組んでいた
to bring the books of those who find
truth and happiness to Heaven.
It all started with Heaven.
すべては天国のおちよ
天国を滅ぼさなけりゃ
Unless you destroy Heaven,
you'll never truly exact revenge.
あんたの復讐なんて　何の意味もないのさ
そのための鍵となるのが　菫の咎人と言ったか
And you said the Violet Sinner
is the key to all this?
Yes. The Violet Sinner is in
love with a certain man.
ああ　菫の咎人はある男に恋をした
彼女の恋が成就するとき　天国は滅びる
If her love succeeds, Heaven will falter.
Noloty...
ノロティ
I will fight, as a dweller in your world.
お前の世界の住人として　俺は戦う
I will destroy Heaven, the root of all evil,
全ての元凶となった天国を滅ぼし
and offer the world to you.
この世界を　お前に捧げる
A feather in the air captures the dream
It's swimming in the darkness,
pretending to be flying
Let's ask the sad blue sky for the answer
Bang on the closing door (Forcefully)
Sneak out and greet for one last time
"Who did you keep on search for?"
I'm lost for words and don't know the answer
Because of the broken love
Now I've lost everything
An angel will no longer come
Dominant Space
A girl's first feelings of love
scattered away, unrequited.
淡い少女の初恋は
Truth,
A girl's first feelings of love
scattered away, unrequited.
願い空しく　散り　消えた
A girl's first feelings of love
scattered away, unrequited.
Now, a woman's final feelings of love
黒い淑女の最後の恋を
Truth, Love,
Now, a woman's final feelings of love
will open the door that leads to the truth.
今　真実へと繋がる扉を開く
真实与爱恋和第二封印书库
Truth, Love, and the Second Sealed Library
will open the door that leads to the truth.